Well, let's see how we can finish off our first game.
Now, just like with the dragonfly, we need to sense if we are touching the sprite.
So I'm quite sure you know what to do here, because basically it's exactly the same as the dragonfly
has, except instead of the dragonfly sensing, if it is touching the ladybug, it's the opposite way
around.
But I want to show you another little trick here.
Remember how earlier we learned we could duplicate code in a sprite?
But we can also duplicate code in between sprites.
So going back to our dragonfly, we can simply click and drag the script and drop it onto our ladybug
sprite.
And doing this will automatically duplicate the script.
Note that now too has this script, so that's cool.
Now all we need to do is change it from touching the ladybugs to touching the dragonflies.
And if you haven't yet figured out how to delete code, you just drag it into this area here and we'll
delete.
Now, what we want it to do is hide when it touches a dragonfly, almost like it's being eaten.
So here we can just go to the looks tab, bring in the hide code so our sprite hides when it touches
the dragonfly.
Now if we play again, notice if we touch the ladybug, it hides.
But unfortunately we have some problems because it's sort of kind of stays hidden and we don't want
that.
And secondly, our dragonfly doesn't play the sound that we wanted.
But this brings us to an important aspect of programming debugging.
And no, I'm not talking about Our Lady bug, even though it's a sort of funny coincidence.
Debugging is essentially the process of finding and fixing errors in your code.
And in programming, there are two main types of errors.
Firstly, they are what are called syntax errors.
And basically all that means is these are errors.
When you write code that doesn't follow the correct syntax or the rules of how the code and the programming
language should be written.
Syntax errors usually prevent your code from running at all, but thankfully you don't have to worry
about this because scratch prevents these errors.
Because you might try to connect two blocks that don't really fit together.
And this is basically saying no.
Doing this would cause essentially a type of syntax error.
But basically scratch is forcing you to write with the use of blocks, perfect syntax, error free code,
which ain't a bad thing.
However, the next type of bug are those that have to do with logical errors, and these errors occur
when your code is written correctly but doesn't do what you intended it to do.
For example, in our game, if the ladybug doesn't hide when it should or if it hides too soon, that
would be a logical error.
Your code still runs, but the result is not what you expected, and these errors will occur all the
time in coding.
But that's just part of programming.
You should never expect your program to work perfectly on the first try.
You'll really be quite lucky if that does happen.
Instead, it's all about debugging and finding all the errors that are in your code and getting rid
of them to get it to work well.
And also, as you gain more experience, you'll get better at spotting and fixing these errors.
So with that all said, let's take a look at these logical errors and see if we can fix them.
So looking at the script for Our Lady Bug, you can see that we get it to hide when it touches the dragonfly,
but we never get it to show again.
So what we could do is bring in a show block right below this.
But you should also notice right away that this is just going to hide and show right away, and happen
so fast that it looks like nothing happens.
And we can confirm this by clicking play.
You can see it doesn't really hide.
What we need.
Here is a weight code block so we can have the sprite hide and then show after a bit of time.
So adding it in between these two blocks and then playing it again.
Yes, you can see it hides properly and then it shows again for a second.
However, we still have one more bug and that is that our dragonfly is not saying yum and making that
cool sound.
Now this area is a bit harder as our code seems perfect.
To fix this, we need to think like a computer and figure out why it's not working as expected.
Let's analyze the situation.
If we look at our dragonfly code when it touches the ladybug, it's supposed to say yum and play a sound,
right?
However, when we observe the game, the ladybug hides immediately upon touching the dragonfly, which
means the dragonfly doesn't get a chance to detect that it's touching the ladybug.
So to fix this issue, we can add a short delay before the ladybug hides, allowing the dragonfly time
to register that it's touching the ladybug.
And we can do this simply by adding a white block before the hide block in the ladybugs code, and setting
the wait time to something short like 0.1 seconds.
This will create a brief pause before the ladybug hides, but it gives the dragonfly enough time to
sense it's touching the ladybug, but it still appears almost instantaneous to us.
So let's test the code again.
And there you have it.
Our very first game is working and all the bugs have been squished and debugged.
Really, really great work on getting to this point.
You are now pretty much I could say a game developer, so put that on your resume, but get ready to
make some far more exciting games than this in the next sections.